Finding aid to the Christine M. Shelton papers SSC.MS.00627
Sophia Smith Collection
Christine M. Shelton papers
1964-2016
Sophia Smith Collection
Shelton, Christine
SSC.MS.00627
42 linear feet (38 boxes, 1 oversize, 1 flat file) 19 record cartons, 1 oversize flat box, 1 flat file 20 boxes of unspecified size
Professor, Exercise and Sport Studies. Materials documenting Shelton's work as Smith College professor of Exercise and Sports Studies, as consultant for various girl's and women's sports organizations, and as a presenter at national and international conferences and workshops concerning advocacy for women's sports. Documentation of Shelton's work with the International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG), the International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women (IAPESGW), and the 1996 Olympic Games in Atlanta is also included.
Conditions Governing Access
According to the terms of the deed of gift, this collection is open without restrictions. However, during accessioning, the following boxes were found to contain student and personnel records, and must therefore be screened before researchers can access them: Acc.#08S-79, boxes 1-4, Acc#10S-72, boxes 1-2, and Acc.#12S-67, box 9; Acc.#16S-62--one folder with student grade rosters closed and moved to Misc. Collections--closed portions box in 62A.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Christine Shelton began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2008 (08S-79), and made additional donations in 2010 (10S-72), 2012 (12S-67), and 2016 (16S-62). Additionally, some papers belonging to Christine Shelton were sent to the SSC by Carole Oglesby in 2018 (2018-S-0007). Additional papers were sent by Christine Shelton in October of 2018 (2018-S-0071). In 2019, one letter document box was transferred from the Carole Oglesby papers into this collection.
Biographical / Historical
Christine M. Shelton earned her B.A. from Madison College in Virginia and her M.S. from James Madison University. She was professor of exercise and sport studies at Smith College, and taught primarily in the graduate program. At the graduate level she taught courses in philosophy and ethics, current issues, and sport pedagogy, and coordinates the coaching practicum. Within the minor, Shelton co-taught the undergraduate course on Sport and the American Dream, and was a performance instructor of tennis. She also served as the co-chair of the Project on Women and Social Change at Smith College. Beyond Smith College, Shelton is involved in national and international organizations that promote increased opportunities for girls and women in sports, including the International Working Group on Women and Sport and the International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid currently provides detailed description of only the most recent additions to this collection. Earlier accessions of materials are described in unpublished container lists that can be sent to you upon request by contacting specialcollections@smith.edu
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies.
Related Materials
Associated material in the International Association for Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women Records.
Scope and Contents
Materials documenting Shelton's work as Smith College professor of Exercise and Sports Studies, as consultant for various girl's and women's sports organizations, and as a presenter at national and international conferences and workshops concerning advocacy for women's sports. Documentation of Shelton's work with the International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG), the International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women (IAPESGW), and the 1996 Olympic Games in Atlanta is also included. Also includes some personal materials from Shelton's earlier life, college education, and marriage, including correspondence from Susan Borque and Carole Oglesby.
Physical education and training -- History -- Sources; Sports for women -- History -- Sources; Women in sports; Physical education teachers -- History -- Sources; Smith College -- Faculty -- Biography -- Sources; Smith College -- Sports -- History; Agendas; Electronic mail; Faculty papers; Fliers; Minutes; Computer media; Floppy disks; CDs; Physical education for women--History--Sources; Women athletes--History--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene; articles; Women--Health and hygiene--History--Sources; Publicity; Notes; correspondence; reports; clippings; Newsletters; International Association for Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women; International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG); Shelton, Christine; Shelton, Christine M.; Oglesby, Carole A.; Oglesby, Carole A.
- Christine M. Shelton papers addition, 2018-S-0007; Oglesby, Carole A.; Shelton, Christine M.; 2.5 linear feet (2 record cartons)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  These papers were donated by Carole Oglesby along with her personal files and records. Due to their volume and relevance to Christine Shelton, they were deaccessioned from the Carole Oglesby papers and added to this collection.
  Scope and Contents
  Materials documenting Shelton's work as consultant for various girl's and women's sports organizations and as a presenter at national and international conferences and workshops concerning advocacy for women's sports. Documentation of Shelton's work with the International Working Group on Women and Sport (IWG), the International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women (IAPESGW), the WomenSport Foundation (WSF) and the United States Olympic Committee (USOC) is also included. Also includes personal items such as patches, cards, and correspondence.
  Oglesby, Carole A.
  - Conference notes and materials, 1979-1987; 18 folders (18 folders) (Box 11)
  - WomenSport Foundation (WSF) papers, 1982-1992; 3 folders (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - United States Olympic Committee (USOC) papers, 1980-1985; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Pamphlets and publications, 1978-1987; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 11)
  - Public school PE files, 1982-1985; 10 folders (10 folders) (Box 12)
  - National Association for Girls and Women in Sport (NAGWS), 1979-1985; 19 folders (19 folders) (Box 12)
  - Notes and correspondence, 1979-1994; 2 folders (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Cards, patches, and personal notes, 1980-1990; 2 folders (1 folder and 1 card envelope) (Box 12)
  - Various organization files, 1980-1987; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 12)
- Christine M. Shelton papers further addition, 2018-S-0071; 3.75 linear feet (3 record cartons); 6 items (4 floppy disks, 2 CDs)
  Donated by Chris Shelton
  This accession contains information on conferences and organizations Shelton participated in, papers from her teaching career at Smith and elsewhere, presentations, and lectures, and information from projects and research Shelton conducted. Also includes personal and professional materials from Shelton's early life and personal correspondence to a number of people, including Susan Borque and Carole Oglesby.
  Floppy disks; CDs; Photographs.
  - Presentation and lecture materials (multiple conferences, speeches), 1974-2006; 14 folders (14 folders) (Box 1)
  - Projects and research, including for the Encyclopedia of Women in Sport and on various female athletes, 1983-2006; 28 folders (28 folders) (Box 1)
  - Academic materials from classes taught by Shelton, 1986-2016; 6 folders (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Conference and organization papers, 1987-2014; 27 folders (27 folders) (Box 2)
  - Bank of America court case papers, 2004-2007; 4 folders (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Professional notes, correspondence, and photographs, 1976-2013; 11 folders (11 folders) (Box 3)
    - Floppy disk, "Funding article, volleyball, name tags, tag 10", 1991 December 17; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 3)
    - Floppy disk, teaching records for ESS 200, ESS 511, and seminars, 1991-1992; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 3)
    - Floppy disk, teaching records for ESS 100 and others, approximately 1992; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 3)
    - Floppy disk, unlabeled, approximately 1992; 1 items (1 floppy disk) (Box 3)
  - Chris Shelton oral history transcript and bio from "An Activist Life, Student Oral History Project", 2009; 2 items (2 compact discs in 1 folder) (Box 3)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This oral history is part of the Activist Life oral history project website. Contact Special Collections staff to request a digital copy.
  - Personal materials: college and graduate papers, tennis articles, and Peace Corps photos, 1964-1978; 5 folders (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Personal correspondence, 1980-2016; 8 folders (8 folders) (Box 3)
- Christine M. Shelton papers further addition, 1972-1987; 2003-S-0070
  This series is made up of material that was donated to the archives by Carole Oglesby for the Carole Oglesby papers, in accession 2003-S-0070. In 2019, the material was moed from Oglesby's papers into the papers of her longtime partner, Chris Shelton.
  - American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (AAHPERD), 1985 (Box 1)
  - Career Design and Career Counseling, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Future Directions for Girls and Women in Sports conference, Mountain Plains New Agenda, 1987 (Box 1)
  - International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Partners of the Americas, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Commission on International Competition, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Vacgia, 1972-1974 (Box 1)